[Music]
welcome back everyone
in this video i'm going to introduce you
to our data structure of the week
which this week is python lists
now you use a list in python to store
a bunch of data now what that data is
well that really depends on your program
it could be a list of numbers it could
be a list of names of people you know
it could be a list of objects where each
object represents
some monster in a game your sky's the
limit you can use
this to store pretty much a list of
anything um
this uh the simplest main data structure
in python
and so i'm going to go through and show
you what they can do
and and how you use python lists so
let me fire up a terminal window
and let's get started
so i'm just going to start by just
typing some commands into python
and so we can create a list
by doing this
basically what i've done here is to use
square brackets and that creates an
empty list now empty lists are really
not very interesting
so instead of an empty list i'm going to
initialize the list with some data and i
can do that
again using square brackets and this is
going to be a list of the
the weekdays in a week so we're going to
add the string
monday we're going to add the string
tuesday
i got string wednesday
thursday and friday
okay it's not a very exciting list but
there we go
so now i've created a list i can print
it out for example
which just shows me exactly what i did
before so what have we got here so far
well
what we know is we use square brackets
to denote a list
and we use commas to separate the item
in the list and the actual things we put
into the list
in this case i've put in text strings
representing date of the week but they
could be other things such as numbers or
objects or things like that
and you can mix them so you could have a
mixture of strings and numbers and
things like that if you wish to
there's no particular restriction that
they all have to be of the same type
that's quite different from for example
an array in c
now what can we actually do when we've
created our list
one thing we might be able to do is to
say well how long is the list
so we can print out the length of
the list length of days
and indeed it says there are five days
in our list of weekdays
next thing we can do is we can actually
access the data from the list we can
access
the data by its position so if we want
to
um look at say what's day two
day two of the week is equal to days and
we can index in by the position in the
list like that
and so we can print out what day two is
and we discover that day two is
wednesday no it's not
um so what's happened here um
the one of the things that's really
important to realize is that
indexing operations in python as they
are in quite a lot of other programming
languages
the very first item is not item number
one it's item number zero
and and this is there for very good
reasons it makes things much
simpler in terms of the arithmetic of
how you actually index things if things
start at zero not
one but you've got to be just a little
bit careful to be aware that you know
what's going on
so day two of the week is not days
two day two of the week is days one
because zero would be the first one
so we can print that out and now it's
actually done the right thing
okay so that's the first thing we can do
we can actually access the data that
we've got stored that's a really useful
thing to be able to do
and we access it in this way by its
position
what's the next thing we can do well if
our list is
fixed and can't be changed it has
limited use so
maybe we can add the weekend so what we
can do is we can
take our days list and we can append to
it
add to the end of we can add saturday to
the end of our list
and we can add sunday to the end of our
list
and we can print out days and now we've
got seven days in our week rather than
the five we had originally so that's
great we can add to the end of the list
we can also modify the list we can
remove items from the list
as well now you can do that
by removing just from the beginning or
the end or we can actually delete
by a position so suppose we really don't
like mondays
um then we can do this we can do dell
day zero
and magically monday has disappeared
um unfortunately we probably don't get
to remove monday from our
list of days in the real world so maybe
we should add it back
so we can actually use insert to add
things
insert to add things back into the list
and insert takes two parameters the
first one is the position so we're going
to put monday at position zero
and then what we add back in this case
monday
and you can see monday has come back
into our list
so that's what things we can do we can
add things to this we can remove things
from the list and so forth
um the next thing we can do is we can
modify the items that are actually in
the list
so for example if we get really excited
that it's the end of the week
we can for example get
be all shouty about friday
and now friday has become capitalized
and shouty
um so those are the sort of operations
that we can perform on lists
um adding modifying and so forth
what else can we do um well how about we
won't want to
to copy a list so we could for example
do more days is equal to days
and now we can print out what more days
is
and it's the same content as days
now suppose in more days we we don't
want to be so excited about fridays we
can then
go and we can change that item back more
days
for is equal to friday as it was before
and we can print out more days and
everything has changed as we expected
but not quite because if we look at
what's happened to the our original list
days that's changed too
now that can be a bit of surprise we
thought we'd made a copy of the list
when we did this
but that's not what happened what
happened instead was
it gave create another name more days
and associated it with the same
list that the name days was associated
with didn't make a copy
so we now have only one list but two
names for it
which sometimes is what you want and
sometimes is not what you want
if you actually want to make a copy of
the list
we can do copy of days
and we do that we actually have to
explicitly say we really really really
do want
python to copy it and of course copying
is more expensive because you have to go
through and create a copy of each
integer
items but if we do that then we can
print it
copy of days
and that one actually um
has same data and we can then for
example
we can delete the
original days we can delete the weekend
so we can delete
six and we can delete five
and now what we'll see is that we've
changed days
but copy of days really is a copy it's
it was not changed by by those
operations so now we have two lists
rather than one
so those are the main operations that we
actually perform on a list
um but that's perhaps not quite so
useful what we often want to do is to go
through
and access all of the data in the list
and so
to do that i'm going to actually have to
fire up an editor
and show you how to actually access
all the items so now let's
create our list again
one day i can't type today
tuesday
wednesday
really having trouble typing
okay so that's our list back where we
were
now how are we going to go through and
say print out
all of the elements of the list well
there's more than one way to do this
so we'll try it in two different ways
the first way we're going to use a
python
for loop and so for a day num
in range
zero to length of days
we're going to mr bracket outlet
i'm going to for each of those print out
both the day num itself
and the contents of that part of the day
so
like that okay so
let's run this and then we'll come back
and look at how it actually works
so first of all
what we see is it's run through and it's
printed out on each line
the position in the list and the content
of that position
okay so what's going on here um this
structure four will let us go through a
a set of data um and and do
the same operation on each of those
things in a set of data so what's a set
of data here well what we've
done is for day num is in range 0 to len
days
and so what this range will do is it
will create
it will generate each time through the
next one in the sequence so with the
first time
through this little loop it will
generate
zero the next time through it will
generate one and then it will generate
two and then it will generate three
all the way up to len days minus one so
it will
if len days is is five this will go up
to number four
and actually that's what we want for
accessing the items from the list
so each time through this variable day
num will take on a different value the
first time it will take on the value
zero the second time we'll take on the
value one and so forth
and so this is going to go through
five times because range from zero to
then days
minus one is five elements print out the
five elements of our list
and each time we're printing out both
the number
that comes from the range and the
element of days
that is associated with that particular
number and so
if we run that again it will
it will print out the um each time that
each number so day numb took on value 0
the first time
value 1 the second time and so forth
going through the list
so that's the first way that we can
actually access
the data from the list now
there's another way of doing it which is
a little bit more
pythonic and that's to actually
for day in days
now we'll just print out day
and this will let us iterate over the
list
each time the variable day will be set
first time to the first element of the
list
second time through to the second
element of the list and so forth
and so if we run that
here we get monday tuesday wednesday
thursday and friday which is the more
pythonic way to actually access the data
from the list
so that's really the basics of accessing
modifying deleting
appending and changing items of list
python this is a very very flexible data
structure
and that's really all you need to know
for now about
how lists work now next week we're going
to look
at how lists perform but for now all i
really want to know is
how do lists work how do you use them
and i think we've covered that just
about enough
okay see you next time
[Music]
you